Finding Aid for Media Resources Center (University of Michigan) films and videotapes, 1930s and 1948-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Series B, Understanding Our World
  - Freedom in Threatened Society 1962, Ten part program hosted by Hugh Fleetwood, UM-Phil.
    - Freedom and Labor 1962, 851831-B-110-5; University of Michigan authorities discuss the civil rights and basic freedoms of the American worker and the responsibilities of government, management and labor unions. Features: Sanford Kadish, UM-Law; Jerold Israel, UM-Law; Stephen Tonsor, UM-Hist; Albert Steigerwalt
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #384, Pos. #693
      - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
      - Streaming File:, 851831-B110-5.flv
    - Freedom and Education 1962, 851831-B-110-6; University of Michigan faculty authorities discuss academic freedom and academic responsibility as fundamental conditions of a free society. Features: Nicholas Kazarinof UM-Math.; Jerold Israel, UM-Law; Stephen Tonsor, UM-Hist.; Elton McNeil
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #386, Pos. #696
      - Streaming File:, 851831-B110-6.flv
    - Freedom and Segregation 1962, 851831-B-110-7; University of Michigan faculty members consider progress and problems in the democratic achievement of personal freedom and equality for all American citizens. Features: Ralph Gibson, UM-Med; Sanford Kadish, UM-Law; Jerold Israel, UM-Law; Stephen Tonsor, UM-Hist.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #387, Pos. #700
      - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
      - Streaming File:, 851831-B110-7.flv
    - Freedom and Police Practices 1962, 851831-B-110-8; University of Michigan law professors examine the democratic guarantees of personal freedom and the right to safety and security of the individual against arbitrary action by government enforcement agencies. Features: Jerold Israel, UM-Law; Sanford Kadish, UM-Law, Stephen Tonsor; Edmund Devine, UM-Law
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #388, Pos. #728
      - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
      - Streaming File:, 851831-B110-8.flv
    - Freedom and Censorship 1962, 851831-B-110-9; A novelist and UM faculty members analyze the modern restriction on the democratic free enterprise of ideas and the major ideas involved in the public and private censorship of books, magazines, films, etc. (print damaged) Features: Stephen Tonsor, UM-Hist.; Jerold Israel, UM-Law; Sanford Kadish, UM-Law; Earl Karr
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #389, Pos. #920
    - Freedom and Conformity 1962, 851831-B-110-10; Freedom and Conformity.; University of Michigan faculty authorities discuss the conflict between individual freedom and the American citizen's urgent search for security in a modern age of anxiety. Features: John Pollard, UM-Med.; Sanford Kadish, UM-Law; Jerold Israel, UM-Law; Stephen Tonsor, UM-Hist
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #390, Pos. #729
      - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
      - Streaming File:, 851831-B110-10.flv
  - Law and the Man of Property 1962, 851831-B-111; Two University of Michigan law professors offer a close and revealing study of the legal meaning of ownership in the modern world. Features: Richard V. Wellman, UM-Law; Joseph Julin, UM-Law
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #385, Pos. #3168
  - Overseas American, The 1962, 851831-B-112; A United States Information Agency instructor questions Peace Corps volunteers in training at the University of Michigan about the U.S. as he plays the role of well informed foreigners. Features: Charles Vetter
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #391, Pos. #730
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
    - Streaming File:, 851831-B112.flv
  - Top Women, The 1962, 851831-B-113; Five top women business executives describe the difficulties of women in the business world in an informal panel discussion. Features: John A. Hanson, UM-Class.; Virginia Allen; Rita Bolitho; Nancy Roman, Hettie Smith
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #394, Pos. #817
  - Ivan Goes to School 1962-1963, 851831-B-114; A comparison is made between Russian and American systems of education by a University of Michigan professor of education and surprising similarities are pointed out. Features: William Medlin, UM-Ed.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #400, Pos. #822
  - Robert Frost 1962-1963, 851831-B-115; A special film documentary on Frost's press conference and lecture at UM less than a year before he died. Frost reads his poem "Never Again Will Birds' Song Be the Same." [Sound quality is poor in some sections] Features: Robert Frost; Donald Hall
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #401, Pos. #823
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
  - From Rebel to Reformer 1962, 851831-B-116; The development of the American woman from her underprivileged 19th century position to her active role in reform movements today is analyzed and illustrated. A suffragette is interviewed as are members of LWV, WCTU, Planned Parenthood, and HOME Features: Robert Blood, UM-Soc.; Mrs George C. Grimes
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #404, Pos. #3008
  - Conflict: The Sentinels 1963, 851831-B-117-4; The Sentinels; A discussion of the increasing scope and responsibilities of America's military establishment with experts who have unique experiences working with the military in civilian capacities. Features: Elton McNeil, UM-Psych.; James K. Pollock, UM-Pol.; David Singer, UM-ISMRD
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #409, Pos. #760
  - Heads and/or Tails 1963, 851831-B-118; Memory transfer and cannibalism in flatworms, training flatworms to run mazes. UM scientists will discuss some new ideas about the nature of learning and memory based upon experiments conducted with flatworms. Features: Elton B. McNeill, UM-Psych; James McConnel, UM-Psych; John Bardach, UM Zool.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #411, Pos. #845
  - Secretary of the Interior: Stewart Udall 1962-1963, 851831-B-119; Sec. of the Interior Udall is interviewed by professors from the UM School of Natural Resources. Features: Stewart Udall; Stanley Cain, UM-SNR; Stephen Spurr, UM-SNR
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #413, Pos. #848
  - Hard Work If You Can Get It 1962-1963, 851831-B-120; Peace Corps Program Officers for the Far East and West Africa programs discuss the different roles the Peace Corps plays: in the lives of individual volunteers, in the countries in which they serve, and in the domestic life of the U.S. Features: Arthur Mendel, UM-Hist.; Harold G. Tufty; John D. Rockefeller IV
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #416, Pos. #842
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
    - Streaming File:, 851831-B120.flv
  - Perspective: Peace Corps 1962-1963, 851831-B-121; Chief of Overseas Planning and Projects for the Peace Corps and UM history professor take a hard look at the Corps, past, present, and future. Features: Arthur Mendel, UM-Hist.; Warren Wiggins
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #417, Pos. #483
  - Seventy Degrees South 1962-1963, 851831-B-122; Swithinback, a leading Antarctic scientist and explorer will discuss the explorations and discoveries in Antarctica as well current studies and research. Features: Charles Swithinback, UM-IST; Charles Kelly, UM-Geol.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #418, Pos. #838
  - Sculpture from a Pump 1962-1963, 851831-B-123; UM School of Architecture and Design faculty member and fountain designer discards concrete structure and creates sculptural shapes in water. Features: Richard Jennings, UM-Arch.; Charles O'Donnell, UM-Engl.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #419, Pos. #836
  - Beyond Form 1962-1963, 851831-B-124; The works, thoughts, and philosophy of a world renowned architect, Walter Breuer, are discussed by Breuer and chairman of the UM Department of Architecture. Features: Walter Saunders, UM-Arch.; Walter Breuer
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #420, Pos. #835
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
    - Streaming File:, 851831-B124.flv
  - Through the Eyes of Children
    - Puppets and Puppeteers 1962-1963, 851831-B-125; Puppets and Puppeteers; The famous Bixby marionettes of Saline, Michigan join storyteller Mary Ann Stevenson in portraying the tale of "Jack and the Beanstalk." A visit backstage to see how the puppeteers manipulate the marionettes. Features: Mary Ann Stevenson; Meredith Bixby
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #427, Pos. #2630
  - Our Other Children 1963-1964, 851831-B-126; A hopeful look at some grown-ups of tomorrow in the nation's inner city schools of today. Director of the Detroit chapter of the Great Cities Improvement Project discusses how the Project works with child, school and, community. Features: Henry Meyer, UM-SW; Carl Marburger
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #432, Pos. #830
  - Report From Ann Arbor 1963-1964, 851831-B-127; Harlan Hatcher, President of the University of Michigan describes his institution's present status to the people of the state. Features: Harlan Hatcher, UM-Pres.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #433, Pos. #832
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
    - Streaming File:, 851831-B127.flv
  - Seatbelts for Survival 1963-1964, 851831-B-128; The positive value of seatbelts are shown in a report of the research conducted by two UM Medical School professors. Features: Donald Huelke, UM-Med.; Paul Gikas, UM-Med.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #436, Pos. #853
  - Encounter
    - Automation and Society 1963-1964, 851831-B-129-1; Automation and Society.;Experts from the University of Michigan Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations and Bureau of Industrial Relations discuss the problems posed to the nation by automation. Features: Hyman Kornbluh, UM-ILIR, George S. Odiorne, UM-BIR, Arthur Mendel, UM-Hist.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #446, Pos. #953
    - Armament/Disarmament 1963-1964, 851831-B-129-2; Armament/Disarmament.; Political scientist and mathematical theorist present their views on the arms race and its place in world society. Features: Anatol Rapaport, UM-Math; Harold Jacobson, UM-Pol.; Arthur Mendel, UM-Hist.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #447, Pos. #952
    - Perception of Fear 1963-1964, 851831-B-129-3; Perception of Fear.; Internationally known UM expert on game theory examines international relations and the value of "game theory" in planning national strategy. Features: Anatol Rapaport, UM-Math; Arthur Mendel UM-Hist.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #448, Pos. #951
    - Mass v. Excellence 1963-1964, 851831-B-131-4; Mass v. Excellence.; Three UM scholars meet to debate "quality vs. quantity" in education, examining the pros and cons of establishing an intellectual elite. Features: Arnold S. Kaufman, UM-Phil.; Gerald F. Else, UM-Class.; Arthur Mendel, UM-Hist.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #452, Pos. #947
  - Report on Arms Control
    - Arms Control and Disarmament Agency 1963-1964, 851831-B-130-1; Arms Control and Disarmament Agency.; Sen. Hubert Humphrey and staff members of the Arms Control and Disarmament Agency report on the founding of the agency, its mission, and the U.S. effort to ease world tension by planning for disarmament. Features: Elton B. McNeil, UM-Psych.; Hubert Humphrey; Thomas Lough; Bernard Bechoefer
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #450, Pos. #949
    - An Effort from Many Quarters 1963-1964, 851831-B-130-2; An Effort From Many Quarters.; Efforts to control weaponry are viewed by UM psychologist Elton B. McNeil and representatives from government, industry, and private peace research groups. Features: Elton B. McNeil, UM-Psych.;
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #451, Pos. #948
  - Kennedy Years, The 1963-1964, 851831-B-132; Four UM professors discuss and appraise the presidency of the late president John Fitzgerald Kennedy Features: Joseph Kallenback, UM-Law; Sanford Kadish, UM-Law; Bradford Perkins, UM-Hist; Arthur Eastman
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #453, Pos. #938
  - Press Conference with Willard Wirtz 1963-1964, 851831-B-133; U.S. Sec. of Labor discusses many significant labor issues of the 1960s during a press conference held on the UM campus. Features: Willard Wirtz, Sec. of Labor
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #459, Pos. #945
  - Nine Days that Made America 1963-1964, 851831-B-134; Story of nine critical days in the Revolution and Washington's successful response. Features: Howard Peckham
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #460, Pos. #944
  - World of Work
    - Job of Choice 1963-1964, 851831-B-135; Job Of Choice:; The guidance counselors role as he helps youths choose careers, some pressures involved, and what youths and parents can expect from counseling. Features: Edward Stasheff, UM-Speech; Delmont K. Byrn, UM-Ed.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #467, Pos. #933
  - Tuskegee 1963-1964, 851831-B-136; The history, present educational aims, and future of Alabama's Tuskegee Institute. A discussion of the UM-Tuskegee cooperative exchange program and a performance by the Tuskegee choir. Features: N. Edd Miller, UM-VPAA; Russell Brown
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #477, Pos. #1045
  - Film Maker and Critic 1963-1964, 851831-B-137; A film critic and a film maker air their views on the role and problems of experimental film makers. A portion of an experimental film illustrates many of the points they discuss. Features: George Manupelli, UM-Art; Pauline Kael
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #479, Pos. #1051
  - Point of Control 1963-1964, 851831-B-138; Staff member of the UM Computing Center discusses how the computer works for us today and what it may make possible tomorrow. Features: Bernard Galler, UM
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #484, Pos. #1989
  - Root and the Flower, The 1963-1964, 851831-B-139; Editor of the Middle English Dictionary reports on its compilation at the University of Michigan. Features: John Reidy, UM-Engl.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #485, Pos. #929
  - Working Scientist, The 1964-1965, 851831-B-140; A discussion of research results challenging the traditional picture of the creative scientist as a man off by himself, working in a specialized area and setting his own goals. Features: Frank M. Andrews, UM-ISR
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #487, Pos. #927
  - Change and excellence
    - Change and excellence 1964-1965, 851831-B-141; Change and Excellence.; A study of the problems facing administrators of large educational institutions who try to maintain academic quality. Features: N. Edd Miller, UM-Ed.; William Haber, UM-Econ.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #488, Pos. #919
  - Hopewell Heritage 1964-1965, 851831-B-142; A study of an excavation into American prehistory and its significance. Including film of UM excavation of a Hopewell Indian site. Features: James B. Griffin, UM-Anthro.; Richard Flanders
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #493, Pos. #1043
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
    - Streaming File:, 851831-B142.flv
  - Dance in Progress 1964-1965, 851831-B-143; Dance instructor and composer, discuss creating and performing modern dance. Features: Elizabeth Weil; William Malm, UM-Music
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #510, Pos. #1042, 2-inch video #765
  - Children Who Hate 1964-1965, 851831-B-144; Training of people who work with emotionally disturbed kids, guidance and therapy at UM Fresh Air Camp. Features: Elton B. McNeill, UM-Psych.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #511, Pos. #665, 2-inch video #458
  - Civil Rights and Stained Glass Windows 1964-1965, 851831-B-145; Dir. of UM Office of Religious Affairs leads a discussion of the clergy's place in the civil rights movement. Hawkins, United Presbyterian, looks at responsibility of black and white clergy. Dotson describes his 1964 voter registration work. Features: N. Patrick Murray, UM Off. Rel. Aff.; Elder G. Hawkins; Paul Dotson
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #512, Pos. #1041
  - Return From Llanogrande 1964-1965, 851831-B-146; Two Peace Corps volunteers tell of their experiences in a small Ecuadorian village. Features: Robert and Flo Griffen
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #513, Pos. #1040
  - Vista for America 1964-1965, 851831-B-147; A discussion of the objectives of V.I.S.T.A. (Volunteers in Service to America) the domestic Peace Corps with VISTA official Richard Gerson, a UM student volunteer, and a Detroit anti-poverty official. Features: William E. Porter, UM-Jour.; Richard Gerson
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #514, Pos. #1039
  - One Man's Folk Art 1964-1965, 851831-B-148; Noted UM artist exhibits and discusses his personal collection of folk art from around the world. Features: Leonard Zamiska, UM-Art; William A. Lewis, UM-Art
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #515, Pos. #1038
  - Horn A' Plenty 1965-1966, 851831-B-149; Professor of French horn discusses its history, early horns are played. UM Quartet plays Mendelssohn. Features: Louis Stout, UM-Music; Jerry Bilik, UM-Music
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #517, Pos. #324
  - Four Wheels that Changed America 1965-1966, 851831-B-150; A fresh and original look at how the gas buggy transformed America. Historic film footage, funny and nostalgic, takes us back to the turn of the century and the beginnings of the auto industry. Features: David L. Lewis, UM-Bus.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #524, Pos. #338, 2-inch video #452
  - Feeling for Justice
    - Psychiatrist, Clergyman, and Counsel 1965-1966, 851831-B-151-1; Psychiatrist, Clergyman and Counsel.; Ten part series hosted by Joseph Julin of the UM Law School. Representatives from various fields of university, professional, and religious life discuss the significance of justice in a democratic society. Features: Andrew Watson, UM-Med.; B.J. George,Jr., UM-Law; Rev. Russell M. Fuller; Joseph Julin, UM-Law
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #531, Pos. #904
    - Justice and the Legislator 1965-1966, 851831-B-151-2; Justice and the Legislator.; Guest authorities from political, professional and academic life discuss the meaning of justice to democratic lawmakers. Features: William Pierce, UM-Law; Gerhart Weinberg, UM-Hist.; Stanley G. Thayer
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #532, Pos. #902
    - Justice and the Judge 1965-1966, 851831-B-151-3; Justice and the Judge.; Three UM Law School professors and Federal District Judge Wade McCree discuss the role of judges in meting out justice. Features: B.J. George, Jr., UM-Law; William B. Harvey, UM-Law; Wade McCree
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #533, Pos. #1024
    - Justice and the Doctor 1965-1966, 851831-B-151-4; Justice and the Doctor.; An examination of the relationship between law and medicine and the effect of law on medical progress. Features: William Smith, UM-Med; Richard Judge, UM-Med.; Marcus Plant, UM-Law
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #534, Pos. #1025
    - Justice and the Accused 1965-1966, 851831-B-151-5; Justice and the Accused.; A consideration of the rights of the defendant under the criminal law. Features: B.J. George,Jr., UM-Law; Jerold Israel, UM-Law; Yale Kamisar, UM-Law
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #535, Pos. #1026
    - Justice and the Journalist 1965-1966, 851831-B-151-6; Justice and the Journalist.; A discussion of the relationship between justice and the free press. Features: William Porter, UM-Journ.; Dean Baker, UM-Jour.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #536, Pos. #1027
    - Justice and the Reformer 1965-1966, 851831-B-151-7; Justice and the Reformer.; An examination of the significance of justice in the area of civil rights. Features: Robert Harris, UM-Pol.; William Harvey, UM-Pol.; Eugene Feingold, UM-Pol.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #537, Pos. #1028
    - Justice and the Child 1965-1966, 851831-B-151-8; Justice and the Child.; An examination of the child in the administration of justice. Features: Tom Croxton, UM-SW; Elton B. McNeil, UM-Psych.; Andrew Watson, UM-Med.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #538, Pos. #1029
    - Justice and the Worker 1965-1966, 851831-B-151-9; Justice and the Worker.; A consideration of the areas of labor legislation and the impact of justice on the worker's position in the American economy. Features: Marcus Plant, UM-Law; Theodore St. Antoine, UM-Law; Russell Smith, UM-Law
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #539, Pos. #1251
    - Justice and the Lawyer 1965-1966, 851831-B-151-10; Justice and the Lawyer.; A discussion of the relationship of justice to the education, training and, practice of the attorney. Features: Marcus Plant, UM-Law; Allan Smith, UM-Law; William Harvey, UM-Law
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #540, Pos. #1030
  - Son of Getron 1965-1966, 851831-B-152; A beautiful and rarely performed medieval music drama, a story of the miraculous intervention of St. Nicholas, is presented in costume by the University of Michigan Consort of Voices, Viols and Historic Instruments directed by Robert Warner. Features: Clyde Thompson; Robert Warner, UM-Music; Consort of Voices, Viols and Historic Instruments
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #551, Pos. #1209, 2-inch video #462
  - Greek Theatre U.S.A. 1965-1966, 851831-B-153; A progress report on the first classic Greek theater in the U.S. in Ypsilanti, Michigan. Features: Theodore Buttrey, UM-Class.; Alexis Solomis; Clara Owens
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #554, Pos. #1181
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
  - Ancient Drama - Modern Times
    - Director vs. Scholar 1966, 851831-B-154-1; Director vs. Scholar:; Translation of the Greek tragedies for modern audiences poses a problem for both the director and the scholar, each having different viewpoints. Features: Theodore Buttrey, UM-Class.; Alexis Solomis
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #562, Pos. #1160, 2-inch video #463
    - Out of Time, Out of Place 1966, 851831-B-154-2; Out of Time, Out of Place:; A classical scholar and a theatre director conclude that the classic Greek plays can be translated for modern audiences. Features: Theodore Buttrey, UM-Class.; Alexis Solomis
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #563, Pos. #1100, 2-inch video #464
    - The Speaker and the Word 1966, 851831-B-154-3; The Speaker and the Word; Theatre is essentially the speaker and the word, success often depends on how well the word is spoken. Artistic director of Ypsilanti, Michigan Greek Theatre shows how meaning of play can be shaped by how words are spoken. Features: Theodore Buttrey, UM-Class.; Alexis Solomis
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #564, Pos. #1101
  - Campaign in the City 1966, 851831-B-155; American politics at the local level is examined in a documentary about a Detroit city councilman's campaign for office. Features: Samuel Eldersveld, UM-Pol.; Mel Ravitz, Detroit city councilman
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #565, Pos. #1005, 2-inch video #448
  - Race, Religion and Responsibility 1966, 851831-B-156; A dialogue on the churches' role in promoting civil rights. The film received a 1967 Mass Media Brotherhood Award from the National Conference of Christians and Jews. Features: N. Patrick Murray, UM; Rev. N. Gordon Jones; Robert Spike; Hubert Locke
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #568, Pos. #1011, 2-inch video #465
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
    - Streaming File:, 851831-B156.flv
  - Jazz Seminar 1966, 851831-B-157; An explanation and demonstration of big band jazz with the University of Michigan Jazz Band. Features: Jazz Band
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #570, Pos. #1016
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 9)
    - Streaming File:, 851831-B157.flv